so what's the purpose to do all these
things you know why are we having this
class and why are we here this week and
why are those crazy people in B Mountain
going to do thousand days of retreat you
know why would someone do a threeyear
retreat and
uh what what what are we doing why are
we doing all this what's the
[Music]
point I mean we I I
why do people do
yoga I I have a yoga teacher in the
Monas you know he said wow so many
million people doing yoga in America
this is a high this is a High secret
practice and I said no Rach you don't
understand they just want to lose weight
you
know and uh we all have different
motivations for wanting to learn to
meditate we all have different goals in
mind uh for learning how to meditate
right and they they are different goals
people are here for different reasons
everybody's here for a different
reason but in the end you are
learning a
skill uh which will change the world all
right you are learning
skills uh which you will take and change
the world you know Jesus came to this
world and Buddha came to this
world and then now it's your turn okay
so you
will you will make a change in the whole
world
[Music]
you if you study these things well you
have the capacity to stop the suffering
in the world okay if you study these
things well we're not just having what
do you call some kind of class or the
point is not that the point is that lots
of people are in
pain lots of people are confused
uh I mean what is this world who are we
in this world what are we doing here
what what are we all doing here we are
struggling to make a
living uh we are struggling to have a
little bit of happiness we are
struggling to have uh some relationships
but in the end isn't it all hopeless I
mean you you you meet somebody you get
married you have some kids and then you
all die I mean you you get a job you get
promoted you work hard you create
something you get re
remunerated you get paid uh and then all
the money is gone and and you died
that's the story of of everybody that's
what we're doing here the whole thing is
uh
crazy you know we we try to be civilized
right we try to drive in line on the
highway and we try not to bite people's
fingers in restaurants and you
know we try to be good to each other but
it's all hopeless you know the whole
thing is we are pretending to be uh calm
and civilized in a world where
everything must be destroyed including
us right and there's no point to life
really uh just make more money that that
that you will leave behind when you die
or do more headstands so you what are
you going to die at a headstand you know
uh what's the point of it all
right the current state of this world is
an
accident uh the current state of this
world is due to some kind of I don't
know evolutionary Quirk we are
evolutionary quirks okay you uh you are
among uh
a gradually diminishing handful of
people in the universe who still yell
back when the boss yells okay you are
among a small minority of living
creatures in this universe who still
didn't get it you know you are at a
certain level of evolution which is
uh destructive you know self-destructive
you you still hurt people back when they
hurt you and then they come back to hurt
you again and and you are not normal
you are
retards okay uh no like there are many
worlds where people figured it out
already and we're like at the back of
the class right we just didn't figure it
out and it's not a big deal to fix the
world okay it's not like a lot of
work just get people to understand the
screaming boss thing and you're halfway
there see if people stop screaming back
their boss or their spouse and they
reflect on how they have created these
things themselves already have the
world's problems are fixed all right so
changing the world is not such a big
thing as you think you know it's not
like
you it's going to take a lot of work
it's just a change in how you view
things right and that change in how you
view things will stop death itself okay
death doesn't exist on many worlds of
this universe it exists on this world
because we're
we don't get it but it's not
natural dying is not natural and the
body falling apart is not natural
getting old is not
natural uh having war having hunger
these things are not the way things
usually are you have to really be dumb
to have those Fai okay you have to be so
dumb that you will yell back at the boss
who yells at you and not understand that
you are making them yell back at you
again okay we are in a temporary what do
you call State and and it doesn't
have to be like this and it and it will
be fixed somebody's going to fix it all
right it might as well be us we can do
it so we just have to get the emptiness
thing done we have to learn to
meditate like the book said and then
January right we're going to do the real
thing so January we'll go try to get to
level four or five or something right
we'll do a 10day retreat
together and we'll just work really hard
on on meditation and then then you got
to have something to meditate on okay
you got to use it for something
meditation is like a microscope and then
you have to put something under it it's
not a big deal to own a a strong
microscope if you don't know what to put
under it right here we go on what to put
the microscope on during the week those
of you losers who flew away and flew
back uh we we went ahead in the book and
we uh studied emptiness you know CU we
thought you wouldn't even
notice we would still be on the same
subject of meditation when you got back
and then we're kind of like I don't know
kids who sneak to the TV and watch their
show and then the mom walks in and and
then they turn the channel to something
uh that Mom will accept RI had a
terrible terrible
uh
Habit uh and I told the story it's
funny uh he used to fly into Bangalore
and then drive to the monastery it's 8
hours to the nearest airport from the
monaster
because you have to go 10 miles an hour
because you have to drive around the
pigs and chickens and cows and
uh so the board of directors of the
monastery and the board of directors of
the C Food fund and the board of
directors of the Asian classic in
Project all these big shots would come
to the city from the monastery to see
ruche to the monastery right they would
drive a whole Caravan of cars to the
monastery but mostly they just wanted to
in the hotel for the night so they
could watch
TV which is not allowed in the Mother's
Day so anyway r j would land from New
York frankf Fort you know and then he
would come to the hotel and the first
thing he' do he'd run over the TV and
put his hand on it and he say TV's hot
[Music]
why are we talking about
this oh yeah you you went away for the
week and We snuck out and did emptiness
together okay so we've already covered a
little bit of this chapter on emptiness
uh we basically we just were talking
about how uh you should study emptiness
from the classics from the big
difficult books on EMP like don't don't
go for some lightweight thing know if
you're going to try to crack emptiness
do it with the heavy RS right here we
go as we were saying inet in
Buddhism as opposed to the usual
historical flow right usually at the
beginning uh when you're close to the
founder of the religion things are more
accurate and more pure and then as the
centuries go by people misunderstand and
people mess it up and especially people
loan on unnecessary junk you know and
then by the 2 500 years later the the
original beautiful 29 pages of the New
Testament get all you know loaded down
with with other people's
stuff I I used to tell my friends they
said do you like the Bible I say yes the
red print you know uh Jesus's own words
those are
extraordinary then you get into this
thing of you know if your neighbor bugs
you poke out his eye or you know all
this other stuff uh but in Buddhism the
opposite happened okay as the centuries
went
by uh the teachings on emptiness were
made more and more accessible all right
so that in the last 500 years we have
toap soapa was the teacher of the first
D and he was very frustrated by the
misunderstandings of emptiness in in in
his time and in Tibet and then he worked
really hard and he he he got it straight
right extraordinarily straight all right
so so the version of emptiness you hear
here the one that we're talking about
the boss all right when we talk about
emptiness and we go straight to your
yelling boss right
uh that's special you can't hear that
kind of emptiness almost anywhere it's
only Ina it's only who who really
clarified it beautifully all right and
you're just lucky you are in a
room where people are talking about the
highest ideas of um in the world and and
in practice how to use them to help
people right with yelling
spouses so
she
uh so it's a special lineage about the
high ideas with which you can save the
world and you can use it in any uh what
do you call
it you can use it in any Walk of Life uh
whatever your job is whatever your
interests are whatever your occupation
is from computer chip designer to
college professor to three-year
Retreat uh it doesn't matter what you do
if you can learn these ideas you
can you can change your what do you call
it you can make revolutionary changes in
your field all right if you get these
ideas no matter what your field is no
matter what your interests are you
can you can change it
drastically my teacher said uh Mike
called me Mike right he said uh after I
got a gushy he refused to call me gushy
right he said Mike
uh he said uh you go to uh New York you
take Diamond Cutter Sutra uh you make
million dollars I'm like R I don't want
to make a million dollars I want to stay
in the monastery he like no no you go to
New York you prove you can make million
dollars with with these ideas in a field
of endeavor in which you have no
interest at all business you know you
you I'm picking for you a a field of
endeavor which you you you have no idea
about it you have no interest in it you
have no experience in it and you have
you have no intention to ever be in
business right I was happy in the
monastery I didn't want to leave the
monastery I left the monastery once in
eight years to go to my brother's uh
funeral you know and that was it and
once to go to Thanksgiving dinner across
the street you know I didn't want to go
anywhere and then he's like go to New
York start a business you know and I'm
like why and he said you need to prove
that these ideas work with anything you
know any anything any whatever you're
feeli this whatever you do for a living
whatever your interest is learn
emptiness and then you can use it to
change that world and if you can change
a world one world you can change any
world if you can
revolutionized business
management which you could care less
about uh then you could do anything and
he just sent me like that he forced me
to go and I'm really happy he did at the
time I was really upset really
angry uh so if you understand what we're
about to Embark upon you can do anything
if you learn toa's presentation on
emptiness you can do change in the world
and that company just sold to Warren
Buffett it reached a quarter billion
dollars Warren Buffett just bought it
last April okay like you can do
anything uh just learn emptiness you can
do anything you want here we go
[Music]
sh J L so in his time in his day so
kaapa read all the books on emptiness
and he didn't like them he said these
are not clear and I don't
understand the vast majority of the
books written in his time by the great
masters of India and Tibet he said I
can't they cannot be
used uh by Regular People to to make
magical things happen Okay
J so he was dissatisfied and he had the
power to see an angel he had made
contact with an angel called
[Music]
MRI and anytime he had a problem in his
life he just asked her him uh what to do
so he asked
you know where am I going to learn about
emptiness you know what should I do CU
these books all seem like they have
mistakes in
he
said okay uh an old Indian writer named
CH Master
chanti he was living in a Buddha
Paradise
okay was
CH according to this he was a Buddha
okay he was hanging out
bu I'm sorry he was a high body
called uh and he looked down on this
world and said people don't get it
people are having trouble understanding
okay so he came to this planet he came
to this
world came to this
[Music]
world so and then he established a
tradition of explanation of emptiness
based on the gous books
okay and this is
the this is the person who according to
the angel of wisdom could explained
emptiness properly he said you want to
understand emptiness you study the text
of Chand
Frankly
Speaking if people like you and I try to
bite off uh jet compa explanation of
emptiness you're going to get a stomach
ache
all right my L used to put it that way
it's very difficult okay his explanation
of tin is difficult it's not easy and it
takes work to it takes work to
understand okay you have to pay for it
no pain no
gain okay you have to pay for it you
have to work hard to get it you have to
work hard
but young young shift to J if you keep
coming back for more
punishment all right if you keep coming
back to it you don't give up keep coming
back to his explanations of
emptiness you will find treasures in
there that you cannot find anywhere else
in the world okay his his explanations
are
tough and they take a lot of thought and
they take meditation and they take a
good
teacher but if you if you
attack uh reality through Jetson ca's
explanation of it didn't to make a two a
quarter billion dollar company in your
free time while you're doing G degree
for 20 years right uh it's a it's a no
break okay I
mean you can reach into reality and make
things happen the day we start started
ACI Phoenix we got a check for
$158,000 from a person I never heard
of
okay
uh no you can make cool stuff happen uh
but you got to work okay you're going to
learn emptiness but you got to work hard
it's going to be it's G to you got to
work hard I can't give it to you on a
play you got to work hard
there's a process for learning about
meditation okay there's a certain
process number one you come to a class
and you hear about
it come to a class some guy gets up
there and talks about everything that's
step number one
step number two you go home and my llama
said cook it you know you go home and
you think about it at
home and then third step you meditate on
it this is the traditional
way uh what Monastery am I from s that's
not the name of s Monastery it's called
t
no uh the name of SAR Monastery is uh
the golden island of learning
contemplation and meditation okay those
three steps
okay so I'm going to teach you
emptiness
says based on
some I would like to give you just a
short introduction
to emptiness based
on and we'll stop
there people are
tired you got your second win those
cookies
got all right just a little bit okay
just a little bit maybe 10 minutes
okay so this is the actual explanation
stud of okay this is a I mean people
study this book my teacher's teacher in
the monastery yesi Wu came from Tibet he
escaped
Tibet uh yes R's teacher escaped Tibet
came to the moner taught this book you
know
so you know people wait 10 20 30 years
to get to this L you got it in a week
okay here we go um
dear we are going to try to establish
that you are not who you thought you
were
okay we are going to try to establish
that you are not the person you thought
you were okay the person you thought you
were cannot be changed the person you
thought you were cannot be made into an
enlightened being
okay because they don't exist
and if they did exist they wouldn't be
change they could not be changed or
improved if you are someone coming from
your seeds in your mind then then then
then then you can do anything right if
the financial status of the world is
coming from your mind you can make a
quarter billion dollar company in in
record time okay if it's coming from
your mind things are doable if they're
out there that's a problem okay you
can't change stuff that's out there if
stuff is coming if stuff is Flowing from
your heart chakra right now then you can
change it just plant different seeds all
right you are not who you thought you
were because if you were the situation
would be hopeless all right you are not
you are not the solid external thing
that you thought you were you are a you
are flowing from your own mind and you
are flowing from the amount of kindness
that you show to others therefore you
you are infinitely plastic you are
infinitely what do you call moldable you
can be molded into any shape right all
right said in his 400 verses
ARA Master ARA who is whose
disciple Arian is great disciple AR
right uh he said there are three things
you want to do in your life
okay first you want to stop those things
which are not
goodness first you want to stop those
things which are not goodness number two
pardon
then in the middle part of your
spiritual career you should stop
thinking of you as
you stop thinking of you as
you and by the end you should stop all
the ways you look at things all right so
anyway some cryptic quotation
stop stop those things which are not
good then stop the you that you used to
think you were and then stop everything
that you used to think okay all right
got
it then you will be a master what does
those three things refer to that's what
we got to find out
now in the first two great sections of
the teachings on the path steps of the
path right called what
inter in the teachings of the first two
great sections of the teachings on the
steps of the path are called teachings
for people of little capacity lesser
capacity and teachings for people of
medium
capacity in those two sections of this
book and every other
L
they we disprove wrong views of reality
such
as uh not believing
that what happens to you comes from what
you do to other
people there are there are people who
believe that something good can happen
in their life without them being good to
other people there are some people who
believe that something bad could happen
to them that's not their fault all right
and and and the the lower parts of this
book The more Elementary parts of this
book are meant to stop that lack of
goodness got
it that that was the first line from AR
he said stop that which is not
goodness what is not goodness refers to
thinking that you could get anything
good happening to you without helping
someone else or that anything that every
bad person you ever met or bad thing
that ever happen to you didn't come from
not taking care of other
people that's basic
stuff
next then step
two try to understand that you are not
who you thought you were Mike is not who
Mike thought he was that's step two okay
what's step
three try to understand that all the
things around you are not what you
thought they
were that's that's Master
talking first stop your lower wrong
views then stop your belief that you are
who you think you are
and then stop you believe that the
things around you are what you thought
they were
okay so I am going to give my
presentation about emptiness following
that
advice so question for
you is PAB going to discuss how Mike is
not the Mike that Mike thought he was or
is he going to discuss first how nothing
around Mike was what Mike thought it
was he's going to talk about Mike that's
all he's justifying his decision of
which kind of emptiness to teach you
first he's going to talk about the
emptiness of
you
first okay in each person it's it's
specific to Christine he's gonna he's
going to explain why Christine is not
who Christine thought Christine was and
he's going to then he's going to explain
why Jamie is is not the person that
Jamie thought Jamie was and he's going
to explain to Jeff why Jeff is not the
person that Jeff Jeff thought Jeff was
okay then he's going to go on to other
stuff but he's going to start with each
person
individually and he's using the
quotation by the guardian student to
justify that approach okay
is there a
difference between the Jamie that Jamie
thought Jamie
was okay is there a difference between
the Jamie that Jamie used to think Jamie
was
and what you thought the flower was
before is there any difference between
those two things is there a difference
between what you thought what you used
to think the flower
was or the Jamie that Jamie used to
think Jamie was is there a difference
between those two
things is there a difference
between an honest
politician
or a balanced federal
budget they both
[Applause]
okay I'm just I'm I'm not saying it's
not true I believe
politicians you go live in another
country and you come home and you will
kiss the American politician feet okay
you will kiss their feet go live in some
other country you know where you can get
beat up and dragged to jail and and
executed for for looking the wrong way
at a police officer you know and then
you you come home and bless Obama's feet
kiss's feet okay so I I'm not saying
that
uh but you see there's no difference
between two things that don't
exist
so the thing that's not there when we
discuss the emptiness of people and
things is the
thing got it because it's not there
right you can't say it's longer shorter
fatter skinnier they they're not there
okay
okay means
but how many EMP I'm getting tired I'm
almost
horizontal how many emptinesses are
there in this
room somebody said as many as there are
objects and people okay because each one
is not what it what you used to think it
was got it each thing in this room and
each person in this room is not what you
used to think they were
therefore there is a kind of emptiness
attached to each person and thing in
this
room there's a chair that wasn't the
chair that you thought it was in the
vicinity of the
chair and then there's a mic that isn't
the mic that Mike thought mik
was somewhere attached to me
okay the truth that I am not who I
thought I was does that
exist the truth that I am not who I
thought I was does that exist yes yeah
that that applies to me
right are are those truths the the
sick no because one is M the truth that
Mike is not who Mike thought Mike was
and the truth that Jamie is not the
Jamie who Jamie thought Jamie was those
are different TRS because they apply to
different
things okay one one applies to Jamie one
applies to M these are different the
they are different not in their content
much but they are different in who they
appli to
okay if you put a hamburger on the
throne or you put a hamburger on the
table is there a difference between the
two
hamburgers only in the sense that one is
on the throne and one is on the table if
I say go get the hamburger on the table
you will be able to get the right one
because it's in it applies to a
different object okay everybody has
their own emptiness okay what you are
empty of is equally
absent okay what you are empty of is
equally
non-existent but the lack of that thing
is specific to you all right
so so PO says it's easier to see the
hamburger on the table than the
hamburger on the
throne what what's he talking
about it's easier to understand that
Mike is not mik than it is to understand
the chair is not the chair that's all
it's easier to work with the emptiness
of yourself than the emptiness of the
chair or the carpet or anything else
right that's not the way what they
usually
say okay we said the opposite the other
thing we said you are so attached to
yourself that it's hard to be honest
about yourself he's looking at it in a
slightly different way he said because
it's intimate to you let's attack it
first because it's intimate to you let's
attack it first I don't believe it's
actually
easier okay but
from a point of view you can say it's
easier it's definitely the one you want
to see first though okay if you can
crack The Emptiness of me you can crack
anything right so on that on in that
sense it's a good place to
start uh there are many different ways
of proving emptiness okay there are many
different proofs to to proving emptiness
okay he mentions a few of
them he mentions there are many
classical proofs for proving emptiness
okay there's the pen there's the
aspr okay all right but in the old days
they use different ones all right and so
he mentions a few names he drops a few
names okay 10 V hand out
youra
uh you
are uh d
means things are empty because they
depend on other
things things are empty because they
things I'll give you the I'll give you
some classical versions of that all
right things depend on other things
because results come from causes
things depend on other things because
results come from causes does it help to
say that your boss was born from your
his mother so you shouldn't get angry at
her not
much
okay it's true that your boss depends on
his mother and that's where he came from
but it doesn't really help you when
you're mad at him all right or her
so so people came up with a higher
version of emptiness they said or
dependence okay is it true that things
depend on their
parts yeah I remember distinctly going
to India and reading this PhD thesis
from Harvard all right somebody gave me
a PhD thesis from Harvard and there was
a SE there was a chapter called
overcoming desire for
growth and
uh and then it said if you have a
problem with desire for girls just
remember they are made of Adams and it
will go away you know like they're just
made of Adams they they consist of their
pieces concentrate on that and you won't
have desire for growth you know and it
didn't work
okay in fact it seems kind of dumb to me
now that they interpreted Buddhist
philosophy to mean that okay that that
is a kind of dependence but it's not
going to help you you see does your boss
have arms and legs does your boss depend
on his arms and
legs does that help you not be angry at
your
boss okay then the higher School says
oh dependence
means your boss depends on your
projections coming out of your mind from
things that you did to people in the
past okay your boss's existence and your
boss's yelling are coming from are you
yelling in the past and that's the
meaning of dependent
origination is that helpful in not
getting mad at your boss yes is it
helpful in destroying your boss
yes okay you see the yelling boss I've
cleaned out 800 employees in my
company over the course of my my
business career I cleaned out 800 people
I had a perfect
building I didn't have a single creep in
the whole building you see I took them
on one by one you see you are yelling I
must have been yelling last week I'm
getting rid of you I refuse to yell for
a month and then they quit you know or
they stopped yelling you see you can
slowly clean out an office building I
did 800 people there wasn't one creep in
the whole building some of you went
there I think who Mama Ora was there
once people went and I cleaned it up
everybody was happy and clean and nice
and happy and you know it was weird it
was really
weird
uh so that version of dependent
origination can change the world right
consider your yelling
boss he is empty because he came from
your projections is that a good
argument is that a proof of emptiness is
that a good proof of emptiness consider
your yelling boss they are empty because
they are coming from how you treated
people in the past is that is that a
convincing argument for emptiness it's a
correct argument for emptiness okay
that's
that's mentioned in the
[Music]
text okay that's the meaning of the
argument in favor of emptiness based on
dependence all
right I'm almost said got
it did you get
it all right next we're gonna tomorrow
okay I'm quitting uh
tomorrow we will go
okay you want to just block that
out the first five syll
there tomorrow we are going to
do all right we are going to talk about
the argument for emptiness which has
seven Parts there's an argument for
emptiness which has seven Parts it's a
beautiful AR argument which is found in
the m Pinda what's
that Melinda
Pinda these are the questions of Melinda
who's
Melinda what's his real name menander
menander or mandra menander Manda was a
Greek okay menander was one of the
people that uh descended from the people
that Alexander dropped off in India
before he ran back to home Okay so so
Alexander dropped a few Kings off in
India and went back home and menander
was descended he was a Greek king okay
and then he got into a debate with a
Buddhist monk in India and that was
recorded uh many many years ago it was
uh BC
200 Alexander reached India I think it's
256 BC or something like that before
Christ was born Alexander the Great
reached India dropped off some King
there and they had arguments with
Buddhist monks which were recorded and
Numa comes from there it's a
beautiful meeting of east and
west uh 2,200 years ago okay it's very
beautiful it's really really beautiful
it's an argument for emptiness which
which they say Aristotle might have
heard from Alexander all
right okay